if I execute this code I am going to be
streaming data within milliseconds now
this is options real live data and as
you can see within this block every time
that we go across These Bars I'm seeing
how many trades are going every 10
milliseconds now the amount of data
that's being pushed through this API
every 10 milliseconds is incredible and
having access to real live
trade options data within this time
frame is really a big advantage of this
API so let's explore how Theta data is
able to do this and what we're able to
do with this level trade level data in
terms of our own analysis so in this
video we're going to be going through
three parts we're going to be looking at
how you can actually access real-time
streaming of Trades data from the Theta
data API we're then going to go if
you're interested in a specific
underlying and specific contracts on
that underline how you can actually
isolate that within the real-time
streaming and then we're going to take a
it one step further instead of just
printing although it's that trade
information to the console what we're
going to do is actually package that and
concatenate that into a pandas data
frame and dictionary format so then you
can use that in real time for your own
analysis so without further Ado let's
get into it let's actually just import
our dependencies first so we've got OS
system pickle numpy and pandas and then
we've got date time as well as the Theta
data classes that you can see we're
importing there so all my code is going
to be available on my website so please
feel free to take a look in the link in
the description now the next things that
I've got here is the Theta data API
Account Details so here I've got my
username and password being passed in
through the environmental variables here
I have real-time intraday streaming so
the first thing we needed to find is a
callback function so the Callback
function is just a method that we get to
generate every time a new message comes
through for the stream of of information
so here I'm isolating If the message is
of type stream message type trade then
I'm going to print out the contract
details the trade details and then the
last bid ask quote
of the time of the trade so first thing
we have to do after that is then
actually create our Theta data client
with our username and password and as
you can see I'm going to have a proteer
account so then I will be eligible for
live streaming I'm going to connect my
callback function and then I'm just
going to request the full trade stream
of options data and this subscribes to
every option trade actually processed
and as you can see it's just printing
out an incredible amount of trade so I'm
going to quickly kill that
so still scrolling down trying to remove
the amount of Trades that have been done
so obviously there's an overwhelming
number of Trades that are happening
every millisecond as I tried to show in
the opening of this video so now once
I've actually closed that trade
information
what I can do is to actually close the
stream completely I'm just going to go
client Dot close
so obviously that's an overwhelming
amount of information to be printed at
the terminal at any given time so we
need an organized way of actually
streaming that data so what I'm going to
do we're going to take a step back and
we're going to access some of the other
important properties through Theta data
API I want to get all contracts of all
expiries for let's say underline Amazon
so the way I'm going to do that I'm
going to set up a get expirations
function and we're going to do this for
a specific ticker Amazon in this case
we're going to create our Theta data
client within this function and then
we're going to connect to the terminal
and we're going to do a request which is
get expirations for a specific ticker
and then return that as data
so
if I make the request with the API we
can see that the root Amazon
ticker we can just get back all the
expirations that the API has within the
database this is a lot of information
historically as well but maybe we're
only interested in the actively traded
contracts into the future so for example
market makers are not forced to show
quotes on all options so we're going to
only look at the main options there that
are not non-standard options like the
weekly or quarterly expirations so we're
going to look for the third Friday of
every week expirations and we're going
to extract that using some pandas date
ranges so the trading days that we're
interested in is from the 24th of
January through to the end of 2024 we're
going to look for the third Friday in
every month and then we're going to find
the intersection of those monthly
contracts that actually are within that
subset
so we're going to convert this from
python list to appenders data frame and
what we get is our monthly expirations
that we're interested in and interested
in getting our live information about
now once we've actually got those
contracts we then need to get the
strikes for all those actively open
contracts so the way we'll do that is
we're going to use the get strikes
function from Theta data so we're going
to build a function again here we're
going to connect to the terminal but
this time we're going to actually build
up a dictionary in Python called all
strikes and this is what will actually
be returning now we're going to run
through all the expiration dates that
we've just um that we've just identified
here in month expirations and we're
going to make a request for every
expiration date for that specific ticker
and we're going to build up this
dictionary by actually indexing or
actually using the key of expiration
date and then returning the actual
strikes that we get back from Theta data
so once we do this we can build up our
data frame for each one of those month
expiries and we're going to pick all
that information down just so we can
have it for easy access later
so as you can see the API is connecting
and for each one of these expiries we've
just returned a bunch of strikes
so how does that look like well now I
can actually reference and open read my
pickle data strikes and just so we
understand what's going on within the
first expiration of my my data frame
there month expirations I've got
February the 17th and then for example
the 13th strike on February 17th is 78.
so now we're going to go into actually
streaming the live contracts so again
I'm going to open a Theta data client
and we'll wait while it's connecting to
the servers that my account is permitted
for so I've I've got the streaming
account there I'm going to connect the
same callback function that we developed
before and now I'm going to run through
for my root ticker Amazon and different
option types for each expiry for each
strikes I'm going to add that specific
contract to the required trade stream
using the rec underscore trade
underscore stream underscore op function
so I'm going to add each one of these
specific contracts that I'm interested
in following to the Theta data live
streaming class so
if we just press go on that you'll see
that I'm only printing out now Amazon
options that are traded and the specific
information so now you can see this is a
lot less
overwhelming the information and I'm
specifically only interested in this
information on this contract so now it's
become a lot more useful so I have
partnered with Theta data on this
channel and the reason I've done that is
because I believe in the power of this
API so I am enjoying using it and how
much information there is with 10 years
of historical data not just on end of
day information but intraday information
on both trades and quote level data that
wasn't even traded in that day we're
talking about hundreds and hundreds of
thousands of data points for each
particular option on each particular
trade date it's really incredible the
amount of data that this API offers so
Theta data API if you are interested in
actually purchasing a subscription to
this API and following along with the
tutorials that we're doing here then
essentially using my code in the
description Quant Pi when you go through
and purchase you will get 15 off for two
months additionally you're going to get
50 off your first month on top of that
so please take a look if you're
interested and I'm really enjoying the
product so far so now if I'm actually
interested in not only printing that
information at the terminal but I want
to add it in to appendix data frame well
then let's build up a dictionary and
we're going to build up a global
dictionary because we need to be able to
reference it in that callback function
so we've got a dictionary that we're
building up here that we're actually
going to be able to combine this
real-time data that's coming through
from our API stream and we go into then
create and build up this dictionary
which will be full of pandas data frames
which we're just going to concatenate
together when we get new information
This Way in real time we'll actually be
able to do re real-time analysis on this
data
so here we're going to Loop through the
options types we're going to Loop
through the expiries so first off we're
going to create a dictionary for each
expiry and then for each expiry we have
a number of strikes so we'll Loop
through for each strike
so now we have trades data for a
particular expiry for a particular
strike we have another dictionary and
then inside that we have either a put or
a call so for each put in call what
we're going to do we're going to create
a pandas data frame
with the following characteristics the
milliseconds of the day so really the
time of the trade the sequence number
the size the condition
the price and then the trade date so
this is all the information the trade
specific information that we're
interested in and this actually mimics
the historical requests that we can do
to Theta data for option Series this
will be useful in the future if we want
to do analysis both historically and in
real time we can combine these data
frames so now we're actually going to
Define our callback function which is
where we're going to build up this
dictionary depending on what trade has
just been done so if the message type
is identified as a trade well then we go
into work out what the expiry was the
strike and the option type
that's going to be used to subsection
our dictionary that we already have
and then we're going to use pandas
concatenate concat to actually take
whether that is an empty data frame or
an already traded data frame with
information
but at the start it'll of course be
empty I'm going to concatenate that with
our new trade information so here we
just have a pandas data frame
with those characteristics and again we
use the message.trade information that
we're interested in to be able to get
the respective columns data so we've got
Ms of day sequence size the condition
you can see here I'm having to do some
string formatting to replace a
particular part of that condition we've
got the price and we've got the date I'm
also setting the index as a unique
sequence as the trade sequence
I'm then concatenating I'm ignoring the
index I I am not ignoring the index
sorry
um because we should have a unique index
as sequence there we can then open the
client terminal
and again Theta data is establishing
um with my subscription which servers
I'm connected to and once the streaming
is connected to I can connect my new
callback function and then add my
specific contracts that I'm interested
in which is all of the Amazon contracts
that are actively being traded in the
future and once trades start coming
through then I can see the trades coming
through here
I can see the different conditions of
these trades
I can see the sizes
so I'm still printing this to terminal
just for a visual effect but if I close
that terminal now I want to see how my
actual data frame is being built up so
I'm just going to look at the pandas
data frames within all these contracts
that aren't empty and print them to the
terminal
so here you can see I'm printing my
pandas data frames that have actually
been actively trading traded in the last
10 seconds that I've just seen and this
is the information that's live and
relevant and that you could use for your
real-time analysis
so in this video we've been through how
you can actually use the Theta data API
to then stream real-live trades of all
trades information that's going through
we've then subsectioned this to an
underlying and all contracts on this
underline that you would be interested
in streaming we've taken it one step
further where we can actually use this
information not only printer to terminal
but then build up a pandas data frame
and dictionary for all these contracts
that we're interested in to actually
then be able to use this for future
analysis or real-time analysis on the
contracts that you're interested in
following now if you're interested in
tick level information like me
especially if you're interested in
historical options analysis and and now
real time streaming of options trade
level and open interest data then I
really encourage you to take a look at
Theta data now here on the channel I've
obviously got an active collaboration
with Theta data but the reason that is
is because I think that this is really
an unrivaled API in this aspect to be
able to have this level of information
as a retail Trader for that price point
is in my opinion quite incredible so if
you'd like to take a look at their
offering the details of my offer using
the discount code Quant Pi will give you
15 off for two months and a further
fifty percent off for your first month
if you start with Theta data so if
you're interested in just getting a
first look in your first month at what
this API is capable of and looking at
tick level information I would highly
recommend I hope you enjoyed the video
and I will see you next time
[Music]
thank you